Today's דף *daf* is כף *chaf* and we are just walking our
way through the סוטה Sotah *Sotah* ceremony and we discussed the מנחה
mincha *mincha* and the sort of what that was made out of.
We discussed the writing of the מגילה megilla *megillah* and the ink
and the parchment and when it was written, only after she took
the שבועה *shvua*. Interestingly, the משנה mishnah *mishna* completely dropped mentioning the
שבועה *shvua*, but anyway. And then the scraping of it into the
water. Then we had this whole major debate which is okay, which
comes first, the drinking of the water or the bringing of the
מנחה mincha *mincha*, dealing with the very obvious ambiguity in the פסוקים
pesukim *psukim* that the פסוקים *psukim* first describe the drinking and then
the מנחה mincha *mincha* and then they say ואחר ישקה את האשה
את המים *V'achar yashke et ha'isha et hamayim*. So we had a
whole debate in terms of that, in terms of what order it
was. But anyway, let's now move to the actual drinking. I mean,
whether in the הלכה halacha *halacha* it's the drinking and then the
מנחה mincha *mincha* or the מנחה mincha *mincha* and then the drinking,
it makes sense that the משנה mishnah *mishna* wants to leave the
drinking to the end because that's the
climax. And actually, that also seemed to be the dominant position, ואחר
ישקה את האשה את המים *V'achar yashke et ha'isha et hamayim*, and
so here we have, after the discussion of the bringing of the
מנחה mincha *mincha*, now we finally have the drinking of the water.
Let's take a look at the משנה mishnah *mishna* on דף כף
*daf chaf*. עד שלא נמחקה המגילה *Ad shelo nimchaka hamegillah*, until the
מגילה megilla *megillah* had been erased, אמרה איני eini, שותה
*amra eini shota*, so we saw this yesterday, but here it is
in the משנה mishnah. *mishna*, if she says I refuse to drink,
I'm not saying I'm guilty but I refuse to drink, then מגילתה
נגנזת *megillata nignenzet*, you would put the מגילה megilla, *megillah* in גניזה
*gniza*, meaning you couldn't destroy it, it had God's name on it,
but you couldn't use it again because it has to be written
for this particular סוטה Sotah *Sotah*. So you'd put it in גניזה
*gniza*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* sort of says there was like a little
hole somewhere that it would be buried בצירי או בצדי ההיכל *btzirei
o btzedei haheichal*. Okay, so that's where it would be put. There's
actually תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* quotes an interesting ירושלמי Yerushalmi, *Yerushalmi*, מגילתה נגנזת
*megillata nignenzet*, תוספות Tosfos, *Tosafot* says ירושלמי Yerushalmi תני נגנזת תחת צירו
של היכל *Yerushalmi tani nignenzet tachat tziro shel heichal*. I don't know
what the ציר *tzir* is. I mean, a ציר *tzir* often is
the thing through like the hole in which
the door peg goes, like the hole at the bottom of the
floor is called like the ציר *tzir* or like on the side
of the lintel the door frame in which the door rotates on.
Oh yes, there you go, של היכל *shel heichal*. Now listen to
this, למה Lama? בשביל לשחקה *lama bishvil leshachaka*. Why? In order to
in order to not erase it, but
to wear it down, right, in order to rub it down. So
that's pretty interesting, that's like a
גרמא *grama* on שם השם Shem Hashem. *Shem Hashem* or whatever. I
mean, yeah, I don't get it. Yeah, I found that very interesting
that that's what was done with it. And why would they want
to do that? Why not just bury it and keep it buried?
Why would they want to wear it away? Anyway, and then it
goes on to say תני לו קטן היה שם shem. ושם המים
נשפכים *tani lu katan haya sham v'sham hamayim nishpachim*, right, water would
sort of flow there and that would also continue to wear it
away and dissolve it. So it's not clear to me why they
were trying to actually, not directly but through גרמא *grama*, have it
wear away. But anyway, they would put it away because it had
שם השם Shem Hashem. *Shem Hashem*. ומנחתה מתפזרת על הדשן *u'minchata mitpazeret
al hadeshen*. And similarly, the מנחה *mincha*, once it had gone into
the כלי Klee שרת *kli sharet*, could not be redeemed and could
not be brought out of the עזרה azarah. *azara*. So it would
be literally it means scattered on the ashes, but what it means
is be burnt in a place in the עזרה azarah, *azara* where
they would burn קרבנות *korbanot* that became פסול *pasul*, which was called
the בית הדשן *Beit hadeshen*. Okay, so all right. It says ואין
מגילתה כשירה להשקות בה סוטה Sotah אחרת *V'ein megillata kshira lehashkot ba
sotah acheret*. And this is why of course you have to put
it in גניזה *gniza*, you can't use it for another סוטה sota
*Sotah*, it has to be written particularly for that סוטה *Sotah*. So
basically if she says she doesn't drink, you stop the proceedings there
as long as God's name has not been erased. And again she
would then get divorced without a כתובה *ksuva*, not that she had
admitted
guilt but because the proceedings are not able to complete and she's
the reason why, she would get divorced without the כתובה *ksuva*. נמחקה
המגילה *Nimchaka hamegillah*, now let's say the מגילה megilla. *megillah* has already
been erased ואמרה איני eini, שותה *v'amra eini shota*, and then she
says I refuse to drink. But she did not admit guilt. If
she were to admit guilt at this time you would stop it
even though the מגילה *megillah* had been erased, but she's not admitting
guilt. So in that case, and there we are, we erased God's
name and now she wants us to not go through with it,
then we're not going to listen. מערערין אותה ומשקין אותה על כרחה
*M'ar'arin otah u'mashkin otah al karchah*, you sort of you rile her
up or whatever, you confuse
her and you force her, like before we mentioned some type of
a vise to keep her mouth open and you force her to
drink against her will. Okay, because אינה מספקת לשתות Eina maspeket lishtot,
*eina maspeket lishtot*, now okay so one way or another if she's
not allowed, once the name is erased she's not allowed to back
out. So whether we force her to drink or whether she drinks
willingly, now we're going to deal with the result of the drinking.
Okay, by the way before we do that, let's look at another
little תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, actually in the middle of the previous תוספות
Tosfos *Tosafot*, in the end of the first. of the wide lines,
the last of the wide lines: נמחקה מגילה Nimechaka megillah, ואמרה איני
שותה, he's still quoting ירושלמי, מערין אותה. mearin otah. למה? Why do
you force her to
drink? שגרמה לשם שימחק Shegarma lashem sheyimachak because because of her she
was silent until now we erased God's name we're not going to
let that go to waste unless she actually comes out with a
full admission. כמה ימחק? Kama yimachak? Now, how much? כמה ימחק? Kama
yimachak? How much of it needs to be erased up to the
point that we now are going to force her and she can't
just say I refuse? So תני רבי חנינא בית שמאי אומרים אות
אחת בית הלל אומרים שתי אותיות Tani Rabbi Chanina Beit Shammai omrim
ot achat Beit Hillel omrim shtei otiyot presumably one or two letters.
אמר רבי אילא טעמיה דבית הלל כדי לכתוב יוד הא Amar Rabbi
Ila taameih deBeit Hillel kedei lichtov Yud Hei part of God's name.
Now it sounds like, is that the name, is that would be
the same thing?
In other words, yeah, I mean actually איסור מחיקת השם issur mechikat
hashem could be even if you erase one letter of the שם.
But this is actually, so that's a good point, you might be
עובר over on מחיקת השם mechikat hashem before you actually erase God's
name. Maybe that's בית שמאי's Beit Shammai position. Anyway, it does sound
like from the way this is phrased that they have to get
to God's name, right? Let's say they erased, I mean I guess
what does it start with? I guess it was the מחלוקת machloket
about where you start, but anyway יתן השם אותך, Yitein Hashem otach,
at least there's the word יתן Yitein beforehand. Let's say they erased
the word יתן Yitein before erasing שם השם. shem Hashem, It sounds
like the ירושלמי they would have to get to שם השם. Okay,
so you make her, so she drinks or she was made to
drink, and now we get to finally the effect of the water.
Let's take look.
I don't know if this is presupposing what we hit before, it
can be she's חוזרת מחמת בריאות? chozeret machmat beriut?
Yeah, presumably that would matter according to at least that שיטה shita
of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Yeah, well the משנה mishnah isn't saying
anything. Yeah, well that was all read into a רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva position, that so it's clearly the משנה's mishnah. going to say
it. נמחקה מגילה, I'm sorry we did that. אינה מספקת לשתות, eina
maspeket lishtot,
she barely had a chance to drink it, meaning it's a way
of saying like, like right after she drank it, instantaneously, עד שפניה
מוריקות ad shepaneiha morikot
her face would literally like turn green or yellow, jaundice, ועיניה בולטות
ve'eineiha boltot
her eyes would bug out, that's a technical term, והיא מתמלאת גידים
vehi mitmaleit gidim she
her face is like feel like her veins are like pronounced out
in the, or גיד gid can mean sinews, but also probably it
could mean like the veins in
her face, is it?
Right, well רש"י Rashi I think says, yeah it could be the
whole body, but
רש"י Rashi, says הגידים שבלחייה hagidim shebilchayeiha in her jaw נופחין ונראין
כמלאי גידין, noffin venirin kemalei gidin,
it looks like her whole face is filled with these sinews or
the veins are like popping out like popping out, וגם בשרה נעשית
שטה שטה של נפיחה vegam besarah naaseit shitah shitah shel nefichah and
like her whole all of her flesh
is like blown up and like rows of like puffed up rows.
והכי תני בסיפרי כמו שפיטים
מזורקים בה, Vehachi tani beSifri kemo shepitim mezurakim bah, like these like
poles, sticks are like are like inserted into her so she's got
all
these like ridges coming out of her flesh.
Okay, והם אומרים vehem omrim and they say הוציאוה, hotziuha, take her
out שלא תטמא העזרה, shelo tetamei haazarah, that she should not impurify
the עזרה. Azarah, So that's where we get the idea, by the
way the משנה mishnah. does not say she dies, but because they're
rushing her out so she's not impurify the עזרה, Azarah?
it sounds like
she will die, it sounds like she's about to die although the
גמרא's Gemara going to qualify that. So it's interesting, everybody assumes she
blows up and dies but it's not in the פסוקים and it's
not in this משנה. Mishnah Now we'll get to what is in
this משנה Mishnah
is the presumption of guilt. It didn't say אם היתה טמאה, im
hayeta temei'ah, אינה מספקת לשתות, or כשהייתה טמאה, keshehayetah temei'ah,
right?
It just tells you naturally of course this is what's going to
happen. So again that presumption of guilt is very interesting in this
משנה. Mishnah Okay now אם יש לה זכות הייתה תולה לה, im
yesh lah zechut hayetah tolah lah, if she had merit it would
hold the punishment in abeyance. Okay, now of course the problem with
that is is that then it
undermines then everybody's belief in the efficacy of the water unless somehow
when it actually did kick in it was clear that it was
'ah, I bet that was because of what happened'. I mean unless
it was obvious when it actually took kick in, but there it
is, like if she knows that she committed adultery and other people
know whatever, everybody sees women getting away with it, so that was
one of the challenges raised by one of the תנאים, Tannaim, the
whole idea of זכות תולה. zechut tolah. But nevertheless that's the assumption
of the משנה. Mishnah אם הייתה יש זכות תולה שנה אחת יש
זכות תולה שתי שנים יש זכות תולה
ג' שנים, Im hayetah yesh zechut tolah shanah achat, yesh zechut tolah
shtei shanim, yesh zechut tolah shalosh shanim, she could have different be
meritorious to different degrees and therefore sometimes it could be one, two,
or three years, or it could mean more? I don't know, well
the גמרא Gemara will discuss it. It sounds like the גמרא Gemara
that this is understood to be בדוקא. bedavka. We'll see that in
the גמרא. Gemara.
Yeah, if she did תשובה teshuvah during that
period?
That's an interesting question. I mean could she do תשובה teshuvah even
before the סוטה period, before she drinks the water, forget the זכות.
zechut. Oh, if she does תשובה?
teshuvah? Yeah, she committed the adultery, right? Well, that's not regarding her
husband.
I mean I guess but you know your point is if you
look at it as a type of a divine punishment then תשובה
teshuvah works. If you look at it as a court-ordained punishment, תשובה
teshuvah is irrelevant. There's like a famous response from the חתם סופר,
Chatam Sofer, oh no, it might be the נודע ביהודה. Noda Biyehudah.
I think it's the נודע ביהודה. Noda Biyehudah. He says let's say
I don't know A guy was חייב מיתה, chayav misa, right? For
anything, even if it was בין אדם למקום, bein adam lamakon, you
know, חילול שבת, chilul shabbos, there was עדים eidim and התראה, hasraah,
חייב מיתה, chayav misa, and he sincerely did תשובה teshuva before they
executed him. He says, we'll still execute him. Like, you know, this
is a law for the civil court, you know, and God, if
God wants to forgive him, that's God's business, but like, very important
because this, you know, the difference between תשובה teshuva as something between
God and the person and not between how we relate to the
person, and we have to do, you know, follow different parameters. I've
always felt that that and other things are very important, you know,
when somebody basically is caught in a scandal, particularly like a case
about sex abuse or things like that taking advantage, and then he
says like, oh, I've done תשובה, teshuva, and people say, oh, well,
we're supposed to believe in תשובה, teshuva, you know? It's like, that's
between him and God, not between him and the community. Like, that
has, that requires other standards. But anyway, but that so you're right
though, to the degree you see this as just a divine punishment,
maybe תשובה teshuva should work, but as was pointed out, it's also
to determine for her husband, you know, and can her husband continue
living with her? And, you know, to the degree that this whole
thing has been made a court-supervised process with witnesses, and you know,
and even the court remember, they first came to the court and
the court sent her to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So, you
know, it seems like we're seeing this more as a while we
need God's help to make this happen, right, it seems like it's
not something that's just between her and God. But an interesting question,
right? I mean, yeah, but presumably not. Okay, but it will but
it will cause, you know, it but I guess your point is,
look, if זכות תולה zechus toleh suspends it, it does sound like
it's just between her and God and a type of a divine
punishment, right? Because it's out of the control of the court. And,
you know, the other question is, as going back to Dov's point,
right, which is an excellent point, which is, okay, they do the
procedure and everything looks hunky-dory, so husband and wife go back to
having a mar you know, sleeping together and resuming marital re you
know, their marriage, and then two years later it turns out that
she actually was guilty, right? What does that do for the husband's
suspicions and the fact that he actually so the whole idea of
זכות תולה zechus toleh is very disruptive to this whole idea. On
the other hand, one imagines that, you know, if they did this
procedure, one wonders how often did it actually really work, you know?
Did she actually like blow up? So how do you explain when
it's not working and it's supposed to work, right? So the גמרא
Gemara has all these explanations of why it might not work. If
he's not מנוקה מעוון, menukeh me'avon, if she has זכות, zechus, you
know, there's all these things to explain it why you know, and
one wonders if that didn't come up from a period you know,
when it was not having the effect it was supposed to have,
yeah.
Which brings up the possibility that maybe this is all about getting
her back together with her husband and silencing her husband.
Right, exactly. But I think it is a good question that I
wasn't thinking about, you know, that Dov that you point out, which
is that even if the besides the fact that if it doesn't
work right away, it'll it'll make, you know, it'll like undermine people's
its reputation and you know, and people's belief in its efficacy.
Also like how will a how, you know, how will the husband
be able to re how will they be able to resume marital
relations, right? I mean, if it hasn't really proven anything immediately. If
it's like known that it doesn't prove anything immediately, then what are
you supposed to do with that? Like, wait two or three years
after till you decide whether it was, you know, what it meant?
I don't know.
So the
גמרא Gemara goes on the משנה Mishnah.
goes on, thank you. מכאן אומר בן עזאי mikan omer Ben Azzai
from here Ben Azzai said, חייב אדם ללמד את בתו תורה. chayav
adam lelamed es bito Torah. Ah, you see? שאם תשתה תדע שזכות
תולה לה. she'im tishteh teda she'zechus toleh lah. Exactly this. She's going
to drink. She's going to think that, hey, I committed adultery and
it didn't work. It must be this whole thing is a fraud.
Ah, but if you teach her תורה Torah and you teach her
this הלכה halacha that that sometimes זכות zechus is תולה, toleh, then
she'll understand that it wasn't because the מים, mayim, the waters, don't
work. This actually is part of the system. So she'll understand and
she won't it won't
be like she she commits well, that's the next line.
That's the response. So the you know, the more you know, the
more you have faith in the system. You understand how things are
working.
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, כל המלמד את בתו תורה כאילו
מלמדה תפלות. kol hamelamed es bito Torah ke'ilu melamdah tiflus. No, it's
like you teach her תפלות tiflus which usually has to mean like
sort of sexual it has a sexual connotation.
Well, there's a question, how does they translate it?
Birnbaum actually translates it promiscuity.
Promiscuity, yeah. That's clear from the next line anyway. I mean, I
know that because this is taken out of context, it's normally translated
as as if he teaches her, I don't know,
like trivial stuff, right? But that's not true. The context is exactly
what Michael said back. It says, well, she won't you know, the
more you know, the more you understand how the system works, then
you have trust in the system, but you also know how to
work the system. You know how to how to you know, how
to go through the loopholes. So therefore, if you teach her הלכה
Halachic this, then she'll figure out, hey, I can commit adultery and
I could get around it, you know? I'll have זכות, zechus, etc.
Of course, זכות zechus just תולה toleh it doesn't totally get her
off the hook, but anyway, but you know, that's an interesting question,
right? A little knowledge is a dangerous thing. Knowledge increases your, you
know, commitment
to
the
whole to
the system.
That would apply to men as well as women, not necessarily for
promiscuity, but anybody who's been through נזיקין Nezikin can figure out perfectly
technically permissible ways of cheating in business.
So that's an interesting question which is why the focus on women,
right? Is it because well women were the class that were basically
not educated in society, so we're able to sort of like discuss
whether it's a good idea or not a good idea, whereas men
are fundamentally educated and there's a מצוה Mitzvah of תלמוד תורה, Talmud
Torah, so it doesn't really matter if we feel that there's some
like negatives. Actually, you know, חנניה, Hananiah, you were just mentioning the
משנה Mishnah כלים. Keilim. The משנה Mishnah כלים, Keilim, one of the
discussions actually spoke about a כלי in
which you could I think like what is it like hide money
or something like that and רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says אוי לנו
אם אומר אוי לנו אם לא אומר. Oy lanu im omer oy
lanu im lo omer. Like if you, anyway, if you teach it
about it, like you maybe somebody could find out this piece of
information which they actually could wind up using in an inappropriate way.
I mean the גמרא Gemara talks
about כל הלומד שלא לשמה... מוטב לו שלא נברא, Kol hamelomed shelo
lishma... mutav lo shelo nivra, which is a certain type of שלא
לשמה, shelo lishma, right, to manipulate the system and so on. So
it could be that the exact same issue would be present with
men, but what are we gonna do? Men are already educated and
there's a מצוה Mitzvah of them for תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. So
it doesn't matter if there are negatives. It's not up for debate.
What is up for debate is the issue about women, and then
we could debate is this positive or negative. It's sort of like
רב משה Rav Moshe was asked about doing בת מצוה Bat Mitzvah
ceremonies in שולן. shuls. Now of course you all know that like
a few decades ago בת מצות Bat Mitzvahs in שולן shuls was
like the big battleground for women's issues in the שול shul and
so on, very similar to things like today. It was sort of
seen as the symbolism of it, I guess because it was in
the Conservative movement or whatever, so it like it took on a
lot of more weight than it had, you know, than it's not
really a הלכה halakha issue anyway. So רב משה Rav Moshe says
that he was against בת מצוה Bat Mitzvah ceremonies in the שול.
shul. Why? He says, look, he says, you know, I don't think
that,
you know, I'm against this whole phenomenon of like בת מצוה Bat
Mitzvah בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. I think, you know, that guests come
and they drive on שבת Shabbos in order to be there, and
he says I've never seen any boy get closer to תורה Torah
and מצות Mitzvos as a result of a בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah
ceremony, so like I just think this whole thing is a bad
idea, so we shouldn't do בת מצוה Bat Mitzvah ceremonies. So then
of course the person wrote back and said, so why are you
not against בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah ceremonies? So first of all, he
had some, he had an answer to explain the distinction, but he
also part of the answer was like, I can't do anything about
those, those are already in place. But if you're talking about something
new,
we can talk about it.
So one way, it's a very good question why we're only talking
about this in terms of women. That's one answer. The other answer
might be that the גמרא Gemara just thinks that women are more,
and I'm not saying this, like a type of דעתן קלות da'atan
kalos or that at least might be רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer's position.
And like they cannot, you know, maybe it's at least רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer who's against it thinks it's something about women, you know,
that makes them more and we'll see the next line in the
משנה Mishna, that will they're more likely to abuse the knowledge than
a man. And let's read the next line in the משנה. Mishna
Wait, I know I'll get the other question, but I know I
will where I will take your questions. I'm reading the next line
in the משנה Mishna? just to show the continuation of that idea
that it might be specifically about women. So then it says, רבי
יהושע אומר רוצה אשה בקב ותפלות מתשעה קבים ופרישות. Rebbi Yehoshua omer
rotzah isha b'kav v'tiflut mitishah kabim u'prishut.
A woman would rather have one measure and be able to have
her licentiousness, or how did I translate that, תפלות? tiflut? Not licentiousness,
something, what? Promiscuity? Would rather, that's a better word, would rather have
one measure and be able to have her promiscuity.
They translate it as physical intimacy. All right, then he actually calls
it sexual relation.
All right, anyway, something relating to she'd rather have one measure and
more, you know, something more sex or something of that nature מתשעה
קבים ופרישות, mitishah kabim u'prishut,
from nine measures and having to forego sexual pleasure. Okay, so but
again, but he, whether it's most people or not I don't know,
but that's his approach to women. So basically means women are more
inclined to make sacrifices for the sake of, you know, being able
to act, you know, to have sexual pleasure. And therefore, we can't
trust them, it seems like, and therefore they can't be trusted with
this knowledge around issues that they might abuse in order to give
them license to go ahead and cheat on their husbands. And then
it ends with saying, הוא היה אומר חסיד שוטה, hu hayah omer
chasid shoteh, a stupid חסיד, chasid, ורשע ערום, v'rasha arum, a crafty
wicked person, ואשה פרושה, v'isha prushah, a woman who is actually,
um, I'm looking for that word, not ascetic, but פרושה, prushah, like
separates out from physical pleasures. It's also ascetic. Yeah, because ascetic is
like an extreme. I think like abstinent maybe, okay,
ומכות פרושים, u'makot prushim, and sort of lashes of the ascetics, let's
translate it as that. הרי אלו מבלי עולם, harei elu mevalei olam,
these people destroy the world. Now, what's the matter with אשה פרושה?
isha prushah? You just got through saying that פרישות prishut was something
that was rare by women and should be something that they should
be more see, more des, more embracing. And also, what's מכות פרושים?
makkot Perushim? So if you look at רש״י, Rashi, מכות פרושים makkot
Perushim מפרש בגמרא שמכה עצמו בכתלים להראות שהוא ענו וצנוע. mefaresh ba-Gemara
she-makkah atzmo ba-k'talim le-harot she-hu anav ve-tzanua.
So it's basically like a self-flagellation to show,
well, meaning it's like a type of a perverted or a false
righteousness, somebody is acting in a way that is demonstrating, showing as
if they're so righteous, but they actually have lost missed the boat
what real righteousness is. So you got I don't know how Rashi
or... but you got the חסיד שוטה, chasid shoteh, like he does
all these acts that make him that are like he's going to
be very פרום, frum, but he has a lack of basic understanding
of real פרומקייט, frumkeit, or people that actually are trying to deceive
or they're deceiving themselves and they're going and they're doing these things
and they really don't have the true righteousness. So אשה פרושה isha
Perusha would be interesting in this. But anyway, it's not clear this
is רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, it's not רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, but
that gets to the question about is this because of a certain
jaundiced look at women and that's why they're saying that don't teach
your daughters or is it like I said,
it's just because well, women hadn't been educated so we can more
debate whether they should be educated or not. Another question, Charlie.
I'm not used to seeing בן עזאי Ben Azzai making הלכה halakha.
statements.
I don't know, he does.
It seems he's not a common תנא. tanna.
Well, that's true, yeah.
Wait, so then what would be so I guess הגמרא's ha-Gemara going
to say...
Yeah, that's true, it's also a little more of policy than הלכה.
halacha
Question is even when the whole issue came up about well we'll
get to this, I don't want to sort of preempt it, but
when the whole issue came up about like women learning תורה Torah
and how do we פסקן pasken like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, do
we don't פסקן pasken like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and so on,
and the רמב״ם Rambam when he brings it down says like basically
says like everybody is חייב chayav to learn תורה, Torah, man or
woman, אבל אמרו חכמים כל המלמד את בתו תורה כאילו מלמדה תפלות.
aval amru chachamim kol ha-melamed et bito Torah ke-ilu melamdah tiflut. So
אמרו חכמים amru chachamim is not the same as saying that it's
אסור, asur, it's talking about a
certain advice
or direction, guidelines. So yeah, I mean how much is this last
debate a halakhic debate or a דעת תורה da'at Torah type of
not really דעת תורה da'at Torah but whatever, religious guidelines and direction
here.
So then we're going to explain what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua had
you do then. Yeah, and the other is just I'm just interested
in the terminology of תפלות. tiflut. Is this used anywhere else and
where and would it be in a sexual context?
Yeah, it is,
and I'll check it up. We're not going to get to the
גמרא Gemara on this today.
I mean, we wonder people think it's fluffery because they think it's
a ט tet as opposed to a ת. tav.
Right, that that's טפל. taphel. Right, like a side. In the context
it's very clear it has to do with a sort of
sexual looseness or again, what was that word? Promiscuity, I think is
a good translation. That really is pretty clear from context. But people
have definitely, when all the issues came up, now we're debating different
issues around women, but when all the issues came up a few
decades ago about women learning תורה Torah and there were all these
things written about this passage in the גמרא, Gemara, there was like
all these analysis done about the whole תפלות tiflut and what it
means in different contexts. Yeah, but I can look that up.
Is the impetus of teaching her תורה Torah so she'll have זכות
zechut so that the effect won't happen immediately, or is it that
if the effect doesn't happen immediately, she'll know תורה Torah and know
that that's still she hasn't stayed in the system, it's still going
to happen eventually?
Well, בן עזאי Ben Azzai seems to say the latter. He says
שביתה תדע שהזכות תולה לה, she-bito teda she-ha-zechut tol'ah lah, not in
order that it will enable זכות zechut to be תולה לה. tol'ah
lah. It would be weird that בן עזאי Ben Azzai would be
trying to teach a woman how to avoid the immediate consequences of
it.
But you could ask for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, is רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer afraid that the זכות zechut of תלמוד תורה talmud Torah
itself will get her out of it, or does he just say,
no, once you know the system, then you'll know how to get
זכות zechut in other ways? But it's still pretty funny because
it only suspends the judgment, it doesn't totally get her out of
the judgment, but it also I think it also is worth mentioning
and then we have to move on. See I was afraid that
the גמרא Gemara was so short today. Anyway, I think it's also
worth
mentioning to what degree does this debate also parallel the whole question
about what is the image of a woman that emerges from the
previous from the whole מסכת, masechet, right? How much we've seen different
opinions. Is the woman is it the husband's fault that the woman
has cheated? Is the husband just as sort of likely as somebody
to commit sexual sin and who we have we're concerned about? Or
do do you see it as always like clearly it's all the
woman's fault and it's and it's the women who cheat, it's not
the men that cheat. What type of like the whole obviously from
the תורה Torah it all focuses on the cheating woman, but in
the the wife, but in the גמרא Gemara we've seen ways in
which the גמרא Gemara has
refocused or at least included the husband in that picture. So here
too I think it's interesting in the context of this woman and
so on, do you continue to sort of say, oh, well the
woman's going to look to cheat on her husband and therefore she
can't be taught תורה Torah and she can't be trusted with תורה.
Torah. תורה, Torah, right? So that's like one approach, as the other
approach is actually like, you know, that women are virtuous and they
are and it's worth to and they'll want to understand why they,
why the water didn't test them. You know, you want to save
them from suspecting the efficacies of the water and it's a good
thing to teach them תורה. Torah. You know, so I think it's
very interesting, right? It's not just a debate about תורה. Torah. There's
also the question about how you're looking at the cheating wife and
how much are you focusing on her as the sinner and her
as the one, you know, as the women are the problem or
do you sort of have a bigger picture about this.
Oh, but isn't it interesting to me, the last line when they
include אשה פרושה isha prusha in this list of people? There is
no such thing as a woman who doesn't want sex.
Right, that's basically, yeah. That's, well, what you did is, I wasn't
going to say it. That's exactly what it is, that the אשה
פרושה, isha prusha, I wasn't going to say that, but we'll get
to the גמרא. Gemara. But the same is the מכות פרושים. makot
prushim. A woman might demonstrate as if she's פרושה, prusha, but all
women are really just looking to cheat and looking to have, you
know, illicit sex, right? So it definitely seems like that's, you know,
whatever different ways you could think of about the whole phenomenon of
סוטה translates into thinking about this issue right here. Okay, let's take
a look.
But there's also the idea that they don't mention about how teaching
a woman more תורה, Torah, she might be less likely to go
in these directions.
That's an interesting point.
Just the negative.
Right, that's a good point too, right? It might just elevate her
character and, right, that's a good, excellent point. Why didn't they mention
it? I don't know. Let's, guys, well, it's coming up tomorrow.
Well, the משנה Mishna refers to זכות סוטה. zechut Sotah. It's not
necessarily a guarantee that just because they're
learning
that you're going to be right.
Right, exactly, exactly. So alright, let's, we'll see all about this tomorrow.
Let's continue today. אמר רבי יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי מאיר. Amar
Rabbi Yehuda Amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi Meir. כשהייתי למד תורה אצל רבי
עקיבא, Keshehaiti lomed Torah etzel Rabbi Akiva, when I was learning תורה
Torah by רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, הייתי מטיל קנקנתום לתוך הדיו. haiti
matil kankanatom letoch hadiyo. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was a scribe
and he said I would put this קנקנתום, kankanatom, which is a
particular, I don't know, ingredient into the ink, which as we'll see
will make it indelible. ולא אמר לי דבר. Velo amar li davar.
He didn't say anything to me. כשבאתי אצל רבי ישמעאל, Keshebati etzel
Rabbi Yishmael, when I went to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael to learn,
אמר לי בני מה מלאכתך. amar li beni mah melachtacha. What's your,
what's your job? אמרתי לו לבלר אני. Amarti lo lavlar ani. I'm
a scribe.
אמר לי בני, Amar li beni, what?
Oh, well לבלר lavlar also can include, you know, for secular documents
as well. Not just for ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah. I don't know,
I'm not sure. אמר לי בני הוי זהיר שמלאכתך מלאכת שמים היא.
Amar li beni hevei zahir shemelachtacha melachat shamayim hi. Be very careful
because your work is God's work, is heaven's work. שמא תחסיר אות
אחת או תתיר אות אחת, Shema tachsir ot achat o tatir ot
achat, and if you when you're writing a ספר תורה Sefer Torah
write one less letter or one more letter, נמצאת אתה מחריב את
העולם כולו. nimtzata ata machriv et ha'olam kulo. You could destroy the
entire world. Okay, because you basically, I mean it's a little hyperbolic.
I mean so you פסל pasel the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. But
if you look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi explains why it could
be disastrous in terms of the theological message. No, but in terms
of the theological message, אם תחסר אות אחת כגון אל"ף וה"א אלהים
אמת. im techaser ot achat kegon aleph vehe Elohim emet. So
if you take out the אל"ף aleph from אמת, emet, okay, that's
pretty bad. Okay, I don't know what the ה"א he is. אלהים
Elohim or אילים. elim. So if you take out the ה"א he
from אלהים Elohim or the אל"ף aleph from אמת, emet, you've got
a pretty bad mess. Okay, or או תתיר אות אחת כגון בראשית
בראו אלהים. o tatir ot achat kegon Bereishit bara'u Elohim.
So then it would have that something called בראשית Bereishit created God.
So anyway, one little letter can make a huge difference in terms
of, you know, it's sort of like that book that says like
what is it? Like have you seen this? Or it's a t-shirt
I actually think it's right. Let's eat, comma, grandma, and then the
other line, let's eat grandma. Punctuation saves lives. So
anyway, so you know, one letter can make a big difference. Okay,
so okay, שמא תחסיר אות אחת או תתיר אות אחת נמצאת אתה
מחריב את העולם כולו. shema tachsir ot achat o tatir ot achat
nimtzata ata machriv et ha'olam kulo. אמרתי לו, Amarti lo, I said
to him, דבר אחד יש לי שאני מטיל לתוך הדיו וקנקנתום שמו.
davar echad yesh li she'ani matil letoch hadiyo vekankanatom shemo. You know
what? I got something I put into the ink and קנקנתום kankanatom
is its name. אמר לי וכי מטילים קנקנתום לתוך הדיו? Amar li
vechi matilim kankanatom letoch hadiyo? Who said you could put קנקנתום kankanatom
into the ink? התורה אמרה ומחה, HaTorah amrah u'macha, that you have
to be able to erase the מגילת סוטה. megillat Sotah. כתב
שיכול להימחק, Ketav sheyachol lehimachek,
writing that can be erased. Now of course that's about מגילת סוטה.
megillat Sotah. Who says it's true about ספר תורה? Sefer Torah? We'll
see about that in a minute. But first let's unpack this. מאי
קאמר ליה ומאי קאמר ליה? Mai ka'amar leh u'mai ka'amar leh? What
did he say to him and what did he respond? Meaning how
is saying the קנקנתום kankanatom a response to not writing an extra
letter or not? So
אלא הכי קאמר ליה, ela hachi ka'amar leh, this is what he
said to him.
לא מבעיא בחסירות ויתירות דבקי אנא. Lo mibaya b'chasirut veyitirut debaki ana.
He said, don't worry Rabbi, I know, I know the exact spellings,
I'm very careful with חסירות ויתירות. chasirut veyitirut. But not only that,
אלא אפילו למיחש לזבוב. ela afilu lemichash lezvuv. I do this extra
thing to make sure that even after I've written it, nothing bad
happens, like maybe a fly will land on the letter and smudge
it. דילמא אתי ויתיב אקרנא דדל"ת, Dilma ati veyativ akarna de'dalet, and
it'll sit on the little
protruding part of the roof of the דל"ת. dalet. ומחיק ליה, u'mechaik
lei, and it will erase it, will smudge that off, ומשוי ליה
ריש, u'mashvei lei reish, will turn the דלת daled into a ריש.
reish. So I am so concerned not only to get the spelling
right, but to, you know, prevent it from smudging after it's been
written, דבר אחר יש לי שאני מטיל לתוך הדיו וקנקנתום שמו, davar
acher yesh li she'ani matil l'toch hadyo v'kankantom shemo, and I put
this קנקנתום kankantom in it to make sure that it will not
smudge and that it will remain indelible. Exactly. איני, now the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, so that's the discussion, okay, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says, no, it has to be able to be erasable, which
makes sense, by the way, because not every scribe is as careful
as רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, so just out of good, like, you
know, prudence, you want an ink that's erasable, and that happens sometimes,
scribes have to go and erase it and rewrite it, and the
problem is when they make a mistake with שם השם, which can't
be erased, but otherwise, the fact that it's erasable, you know, makes
it especially something as large as a ספר תורה. sefer Torah. By
the way, another important הלכה that makes it possible to fix a
ספר תורה sefer Torah is that it doesn't have to be written
כסידרן. ksidran. Right? Imagine if a ספר תורה sefer Torah had to
be written כסידרן, ksidran, then if you wanted to make a correction,
you couldn't because you'd have to go from there on or you'd
have to go find a parchment that had been written before, you
know, your ספר תורה sefer Torah had been written, but even that
wouldn't work because then it wouldn't be כסידרן ksidran of the, you
know... So the fact that it's שלא כסידרן, shelo ksidran, you don't
have to write it in order, and that it can be erased,
the letters are almost like necessary הלכות halachos for a ספר תורה
sefer Torah because people make mistakes and they do have to be
corrected.
Technically, right, like דברים Devarim before בראשית? Bereishis? Technically, yes. Okay, so
Rabbi Meir was saying that you actually can't have indelible ink. Correct.
Correct.
But what is the story exactly? So we will... let's continue with
the גמרא. Gemara. So first, גמרא Gemara says איני, is this really
true that that was the story? We have a ברייתא braisa that
has a different version of the story. והתניא, v'hatanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי מאיר כשהייתי למד תורה אצל רבי ישמעאל,
amar Rabbi Meir k'she'hayisi lomed Torah eitzel Rabbi Yishmael, when I was
learning by
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, הייתי מטיל קנקנתום לתוך הדיו ולא אמר לי
דבר, hayisi matil kankantom l'toch hadyo v'lo amar li davar, I put
קנקנתום kankantom and he didn't say anything. כשבאתי אצל רבי עקיבא, k'she'basi
eitzel Rabbi Akiva, אסרה עלי, asrah alay, he forbade me. So here
you have the reverse. So of course the easiest thing to say
is it's a מחלוקת machlokes of the ברייתות braisas what the story
was, but the גמרא Gemara wants to see if it can reconcile
it. קשיא שימוש אשימוש קשיא אסרה אאסרה. kashya shimush a-shimush kashya asrah
a-asrah. So first of all, we have a contradiction: what order did
he, you know, learn by and attend to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? In one version it was first רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and then רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the other version
was רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and then רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And
the other problem we have is who was the one who said
it was forbidden? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא שימוש אשימוש
לא קשיא, bishlama shimush a-shimush lo kashya, the issue of who he
learned by, who he apprenticed by, is not a difficult... because we
can explain that they're both true. מעיקרא אתא לקמיה דרבי עקיבא, me'ikara
asa l'kamei d'Rabbi Akiva, he first started learning with רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. כיוון דלא מצי קאי אליביה, keivan d'lo matzi ka'ei alibeih, he
couldn't understand what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was getting at. Whoa. Right,
this is the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who nobody else was able
to understand what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was getting at. But this
was at the beginning of his learning, he couldn't understand רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. אתא לקמיה דרבי ישמעאל וגמר גמרא, asa l'kamei d'Rabbi Yishmael
v'gamar gemara, he went to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and by רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, this is again very interesting, also reflecting difference, not
just רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael was like less on a demanding level
than רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but their approach to learning was different.
That רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael was much more about the tradition, and
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was much more about the sort of, you
know, analysis and the human creativity. So he figured like, you know,
I gotta learn some of the basic information before I can understand
what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is getting at. So it's always that
question also, like do you first learn knowledge and then analyze, or
do you start with the analysis like right at the beginning? So
he went by רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and he learned the tradition,
he learned the basic information. הדר אתא לקמיה דרבי עקיבא סבר סברא,
hadar asa l'kamei d'Rabbi Akiva savar svara, and then he went to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and then he learned how to analyze it
and break it down and so on. So basically, which order was
it? They're both true. It was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and then
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, but it was also רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
and then רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, now, but אלא אסרה אאסרה
קשיא, ela asrah a-asrah kashya, but we do have a problem: who
was the one who said it was forbidden and who said it
was okay or who didn't say anything? So the גמרא Gemara says
קשיא, kashya, you're right, that is difficult, which basically means that there's
a debate in the ברייתות braisas what happened. Okay, תניא, tanya, so
now רבי יהודה אומר אומר היה רבי מאיר, Rabbi Yehuda omer omer
hayah Rabbi Meir, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
used to say לכל מטילין קנקנתום לתוך הדיו, l'chol matilin kankantom l'toch
hadyo, he was not ready to give up his קנקנתום, kankantom, so
he said you could put קנקנתום kankantom for ink for all purposes
חוץ מפרשת סוטה בלבד. chutz mi-parshas sotah bilvad.
So fine, I accept the pushback when it comes to writing פרשת
סוטה, parshas sotah, but nothing else. Now presumably פרשת סוטה parshas sotah
here he means in the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, which is interesting
because, like, since when are you going to scrape this piece out?
Whatever. The גמרא Gemara is going to deal with that. Okay, maybe
you could. The גמרא Gemara will deal with that. רבי יעקב אומר
משמו, Rabbi Yaakov omer mishmo, and רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says in
the name of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, חוץ מפרשת סוטה שבמקדש, chutz
mi-parshas sotah she-ba-mikdash,
that no, he was only prepared to accept
the correction when it came to writing the real פרשת סוטה, parshas
sotah, that has to be erasable; the other part of the תורה
Torah does not. Okay, so מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what's their debate
about? אמר רבי ירמיה למחוק למדינתא איכא בינייהו, amar Rabbi Yirmiyah limchok
limdinata ika beinaihu, the debate is whether you can use the פרשה
parsha in the
תורה. Torah. Now, of course, the point is, but even if you
could use the פרשה parsha in the תורה, Torah, right, we're going
to get to that. In theory, why did you, why would you
have to write it that way? Like okay, even if you held
like you could use, in theory you could use the פרשה parsha
in the תורה, Torah, why would it demand being written in a
way that was able to be used for that purpose? So תוספות
Tosfos basically says that seems to be what we're understanding, that since
let me find the תוספות, Tosafos
I think it's the previous עמוד. amud. Anyway. All right, I won't
look for it, but basically, it's not just to give you the
ability were you to so choose, but since the תורה Torah says
ומחה umacha you have to erase it, and this פרשה parsha in
theory could be used as such, there's an understanding that this פרשה
parsha has to be written in a way that it itself could
serve as the פרשת סוטה. parshat Sotah. That's the understanding, okay? So
that's the debate. If in order to say that it requires to
be done of פרשת סוטה parshat Sotah in the תורה, Torah, you
have to assume number one that if you wanted to you could
use it. And number two because it's possible to be used, the
תורה Torah would demand that you made it possible to be used
and that you wrote it in that way where the ink could
be erased. Okay, opposed to the other position which says look, you
can't use the one in the תורה Torah anyway, there's only a
demand when you're actually writing it in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says הני תנאי כהני תנאי. hahanei
tanna'ei ki hanei tanna'ei. This debate about whether you can use the
פרשת סוטה parshat Sotah written in the תורה Torah connects to the
following debate. These תנאים tanna'im of the תניא tanyia in a ברייתא.
braisa. אין מגילה כשרה להשקות בה סוטה אחרת. Ein megilla keshira lehashkos
bah sotah acheres. You can't use a מגילה for one woman for
to another woman. רבי אחא ברבי יאשיה Rabbi Akha berabbi Yoshiya אומר
omer מגילה כשרה להשקות בה סוטה אחרת. megilla keshira lehashkos bah sotah
acheres. We haven't seen this until now. He says yes, if you
did write it for one woman, so I guess if one woman
said no, I'm not going through with it, according to him you
save the מגילה and you'd reuse it for another woman. Okay, now,
of course, there is a little bit of a problem which is
also whatever happened to the other position about רבא Rava that you
can't write it before she took the oath, right? So תוספות tries
to deal with a part of this גמרא Gemara is completely ignored
that. That if you could write it for another woman you don't
have to write it after the oath was taken. But תוספות wants
to try to bring that other גמרא Gemara in and say like
so what we're talking about is that both women took the oath
and then you wrote it for one woman and you want to
use it for the other. Okay, or in the ספר תורה sefer
Torah example, you wrote the ספר תורה sefer Torah after the woman
took the oath and that's the discussion. But תוספות anyway raises this
question about does does it have to be written after the woman
took the oath? This that was said earlier by רבא, Rava, this
גמרא Gemara seems to be completely ignoring that question, okay? So we
have this debate about whether if it's written for one woman it
could be written for another. So presumably the same debate would be
if it's written in the ספר תורה sefer Torah and not for
any particular woman, could it be used for a particular woman? So
the גמרא, Gemara, this is always the fun thing about the גמרא
Gemara sort of says, no, no, no, we can actually interestingly say
that the debates are different and the debates could go either way.
You could hold one position by ספר תורה sefer Torah and the
opposite position about writing for רחל Rachel to use for לאה. Leah.
Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר פפא Amar
Papa דילמא לא היא. dilma la hi. No, maybe they're not the
same debate. עד כאן לא קאמר תנא קמא התם Ad kan lo
ka'amar tanna kamma hasom there where you can't if you wrote for
רחל Rachel you can't write for לאה, Leah, אלא כיון דאיתקצאי לשום
רחל ela keivan de'itkazai leshum Rachel it's been like attached or, you
know, for רחל Rachel's purpose, it's been connected to רחל, Rachel, לא
הדר מינתקא לשום לאה lo hadar mintikah leshum Leah can't be reassigned
and reattached to לאה. Leah. It specifically is רחל Rachel's מגילה, it
can't become לאה Leah's מגילה. That's why he says if it's written
for one woman can't be written for another. אבל תורה דסתמא כתיבא,
Aval Torah distama kesiva, תורה Torah is written not for any particular
woman. It's generic. So maybe if it's written generically הכא נמי דמחקינן,
hacha nami demachakinan, maybe you can use it for a particular woman,
meaning maybe you don't need לשמה, lishma, right? There is like there
is like written לשמה lishma or written לשום leshum somebody else. And
then there's the middle case, not for her sake but not for
anybody else's sake. So maybe if you say you can't use רחל
Rachel's for לאה, Leah, it means you can't use somebody written for
someone else. But maybe you don't demand לשמה, lishma, you know, it
could be written generically and you could use the one in the
ספר תורה. sefer Torah. So that's one way that somebody who says
רחל Rachel can't be used for לאה Leah might still say you
could use the one for the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. Or it
could go the reverse. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
אמר דילמא לא היא, amar dilma la hi, and here's another way
to say that it's not connected. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אחא
ברבי יאשיה התם Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Akha berabbi Yoshiya hasom
אלא כיון דאכתוב לשום אלות ואלה. ela keivan de'ichtiv leshum alos ve'alah.
When does רבי אחא ברבי יאשיה Rabbi Akha berabbi Yoshiya say that
if it's written for רחל Rachel it could be used for לאה?
Leah? Because it was written for the purpose of curse. It was
written to be used as a מגילת סוטה. megillas sotah. So he
doesn't care רחל Rachel or לאה. Leah. What he cares is is
that it's defined as a מגילת סוטה. megillas sotah. אבל תורה דללמוד
כתיבא, Aval Torah delilmod kesiva,
but תורה Torah that's written to learn from it, meaning that's not
written to serve as a curse, it's written to be a ספר
תורה sefer Torah הכא נמי דלא מחקינן. hacha nami delo machakinan. Maybe
you can't. So the גמרא Gemara very nicely points out that these
are complete there are reasons to argue for and against each case.
On one case it's written specifically for one woman, which would argue
it can't be used for the other. On the other hand, it's
written to serve as a מגילת סוטה. megillas sotah. The other case
has the positive that it's not written specifically for any woman and
has the negative that it's not written as a מגילת סוטה. megillas
sotah. So the debate could go either way. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ולרבי אחא ברבי יאשיה, uleRabbi Akha berabbi
Yoshiya, now רבי אחא ברבי יאשיה Rabbi Akha berabbi Yoshiya that says
that if you wrote it for רחל Rachel you could use it
for לאה, Leah, רמי ליה remi lei כתב לגרש את אשתו ונמלך
kasav legaresh es ishto venimlah
if a man wrote a גט get for his wife and he
changed his mind מצאו בן עירו matzo ben iro ומצאו בן עירו
*u-metzao ben iro*, and then a somebody from his own town found
him, because it has the name of the town in it, so
it has to be the same town, ואמר לו *ve-amar lo*, and
said to him, "You know what? שמי כשמך ושם אשתי כשם אשתך
*shmi keshimcha ve-shem ishti ke-shem ishtecha*." Hey, you know what? I have
the same name as you and my wife has the same name.
Great, let me have this גט *Get*. I was thinking about divorcing
my wife. So ההוא *ha-hu* is פסול לגרש בו *pasul legarsheto bo*.
It's invalid. So basically a גט *Get* for רחל *Rachel* can't be
used for לאה *Leah*, and presumably that's universal. So why is this
different? So obviously who said? The answer is: Who said גיטין Gittin,
*Gittin* and סוטה *Sotah* have the same הלכה *halacha* of how they
have to be written? So אמר *amar*, you could say no. התם
*hatam*, דכתב לה *de-chtav lah*, אמר רחמנא *amar rachmana*. You write it
for her. A גט *Get* has to be written for that woman.
ועיקר כתיבה לשמה *ve-ikar keshiva lishmah*. הכא נמי *hacha nami*, ועשה לה
*ve-asah lah*. But here it here it doesn't also say you should
do it for her, את כל התורה הזאת *et kol ha-Torah ha-zot*.
No, but מה עשייה *mah asiyah*? מחיקה *mechikah*. The erasing. Maybe that
should be erased for a particular woman. That's what the law is
telling you. But it never says it has to be written for
a particular woman. Okay. So so it says no, it says the
כהן *Kohen* writes the אלות *alot*, but it doesn't say וכתב לה
*ve-chtav lah*. Okay. So basically we have a very fascinating debate, which
we didn't see before, about whether it has to be you can
use it in the ספר תורה Torah, *Sefer Torah*. Is it okay
if it's written generically? Number one, א *aleph*, it's not written for
a ספר תורה *Sefer Torah*, for a to serve as a curses
and מגילת סוטה *Megillat Sotah*, it's not written for a particular woman.
On the other hand, it's not written for anyone else. Can you
use the generic one in the ספר תורה *Sefer Torah*? And ב
*bet*, can you use one written for רחל *Rachel* for לאה *Leah*,
an opinion that actually the writing doesn't matter, it's the erasing that
matters? But then again it is interesting that you know this whole
thing that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says, וכי מטילים קנקנתום
לתוך הדיו *ve-chi matilin kankantom le-toch ha-dyo*? In the end of the
day, his objection really seemed to be limited to מגילת סוטה *Megillat
Sotah*, and even there it was like, okay, so I won't use
it for מגילת סוטה *Megillat Sotah*, or worse, I won't use it
for the מגילת סוטה *Megillat Sotah* in the תורה *Torah* if in
theory that can serve as מגילת סוטה *Megillat Sotah*. It sounded though
that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*'s objection was broader, that רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* sort of felt like this maybe is revealing on
all of, you know, the writing of the תורה *Torah*, that it
has to be this type of a writing. But anyway, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* does not spin that out. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems
like at most, certainly at most רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* only accepted
it regarding the מגילת סוטה *Megillat Sotah*.
And our inks today in ספרי Sifrei תורה *Sifrei Torah* are definitely
erasable.
But how? Yeah, sure. That's how a סופר *Sofer* is able to
correct something. הכתב נמחק *ha-ktav nimchak*? Yeah, that's what it means. Oh,
that's what it means. Yeah, as opposed to as opposed to it
gets absorbed into the actual, you know, into the actual קלף *klaf*
itself. Scraping it means it rides on the surface. Scraping it means
it rides on the surface, right? As opposed to being absorbed into
the קלף *klaf* then you wouldn't be able to scrape it.
So we do פוסק *posek* like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*?
Well, I don't know. It's an interesting question whether we would פוסק
*pasken* it would be פסול *pasul* or whether we just in practice
do it because obviously it's the only smart thing to do because
you want to be able to correct it, right? So I but
I'd have to check if למעשה *le-ma'aseh* we פוסק *pasken* it.
That's why maybe, let's say you can have like indelible ink that's
seeped into the קלף *klaf* somewhere?
It could be, but then it's a that's true. I mean, if
you want me to quickly look up. Hold on. Let me take
a look here.
That's okay. I could do it. אלף תפילין *Aleph Tefillin*. Hold on.
אלף תפילין
*Aleph Tefillin* invalid in the רמב"ם *Rambam*. Okay.
So so again, so what do you mean by it's
that because then it would be a problem even if you somehow
scrape the ink if it made like a רושם *roshem* in it
and like seeped into the קלף *klaf*, then that'd be you couldn't
do anything about that, is what you're saying. What? If it's actually
seeped into the קלף *klaf*, you couldn't do anything about that.
Correct. כיצד מעשה הדיו *Keitzad ma'aseh ha-dyo*, etc., etc. Okay, etc., etc.
Okay, או כיוצא בו וכתב בו אם נמחק זהו הדיו שמצווה מן
המובחר לכתוב בו ספרים תפילין ומזוזות *o ke-yotzei bo ve-chatav bo im
nimchak zehu ha-dyo she-mitzvah min ha-muvchar lichtov bo sefarim tefillin u-mezuzot*, ואם
כתב בשלושה במיני אפיצא וקנקנתום שהוא עומד ואינו נמחק כשרים *ve-im katav
bi-shlosha be-minei afitza ve-kankantom she-hu omed ve-eino nimchak kesherim*. So the רמב"ם
*Rambam* says it's לכתחילה *lechatchila* to write it with erasable ink, ink
that can be erased, but בדיעבד *bedieved* it's okay.
And if it can't be erased, then you're stuck.
Yeah. Okay. And it's not שם השם *Shem Hashem*. Yeah, I mean,
what are you going to do? You can't erase it. Okay. Yeah.
Isn't there something some relationship between the divorce and the סוטה *Sotah*,
that's the divorce is like they both have to do with Right,
separating them.
Right. Right. So maybe the comparison like it's a death.
סוטה *Sotah* is an end-of-death, you don't know what they are.
That's a good point. That serves either comparison of the writing of
the מגילת סוטה *Megillat Sotah* and the writing of the גט *Get*,
that they're basically a process that one will, if it goes to
the husband, goes to, will definitely end in a severance, and the
other depends on what's going to happen.
Can be related
to this point, right?
Like it's erasable, because the סוטה *Sotah*, yeah, that's what...
Oh, I'm sorry, what are you saying?
That it's something related to this idea of why
the erasable means that there's a way in which it doesn't have
to be final.
One as opposed to the other. It's like it's not a final
determination.
Right, right, right. Nice idea. Okay. Alright. ואינו מספיק להשקותה עד שפניה
מוריקות *Ve-eino maspik le-hashkotah ad she-paneha morikot*. Now we get to her
face blown up.
מאן תנא *Man tanna*?
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*. Now first we're just saying that
it sounds like as soon as she drank it, her, you know,
it would have the effect. So that's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. דאמר
מקריב את מנחתה ואחר כך משקה de'amar makriv es minchasah ve'achach kach
mashkeh, *Rabbi Shimon de-amar makriv et minchatah ve-achar kach mashke*. Like sounds
like this is nothing because that first the מנחה *minchah* and then
the water, because if you drink and then had to bring the
מנחה *minchah*, the assumption is that the water would not have effect
until the מנחה *minchah* was brought. והכא דלא קרבה מנחתה לא בדקי
לה מיא *Ve-hacha de-lo karvah minchatah lo badki lah maya*,
because we know what whatever position you hold about the order, until
the מנחה's brought, the water won't be effective.
דכתיב dechtiv מנחת זכרון היא מנחת זכרון מזכרת עון Minchas zikaron hee
minchas zikaron mazkeres avon that the מנחה makes the sin remembered and
remembered usually means there's a worldly consequence, like God is going to
do something about that. So therefore, without the מנחה it won't have
the effect. So if it has the effect immediately, it must be
that the מנחה happened beforehand. So the גמרא Gemara says אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, let's look at the end. יש לה זכות היתה תולה
לה, Yesh lah zachus haysa toulah lah, if there was a merit
it would suspend it. אתו רבנן, Asu rabanan, that's the rabbis who
argue on רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon a different- a different position of
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon ורבי שמעון אמר אין זכות תולה במים המאררים,
VeRabbi Shimon amar ein zachus toulah bamayim hamararim, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
was the one that objected to this whole idea of זכות תולה,
zachus toulah, it undermines the whole efficacy or the whole perceived efficacy
of the water. So the גמרא Gemara says what is it? Because
clearly we're starting with רבי שמעון because it says we're assuming the
מנחה came first, but the idea of זכות תולה zachus toulah is
a non-רבי שמעון position. So אמר רב חסדא הא מני רבי עקיבא
היא, Amar Rav Chisda ha mani Rabbi Akiva hee, fine, it's a
third position, דאמר מקריב את מנחתה ואחר כך משקה, we saw a
ברייתא braisa that רבי עקיבא said מנחה comes before the drinking. ובזכות,
uv'zachus, but when it comes to the matter of זכות, zachus, סבר
לה כרבנן, savar lah kerabanan, he would hold that it would be
תולה, toulah, and תוספות actually says that we had a tradition or
there's actually a ספרא Sifra that has- or ספרי that has רבי
עקיבא explicitly also agreeing to the idea of זכות תולה. zachus toulah.
Okay, so fine, they're not related positions. You could hold מנחה first
and also hold like that the idea is זכות תולה. zachus toulah.
Okay, והם אומרים הוציאוה, veheim omrim hotziuha, and they said take her
out. So now this is very interesting because everybody assumes she's going
to burst and die, but it didn't say it in the תורה,
it didn't say it in the משנה, although you said what? טמאה
Tmeia sounds like that. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי
טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why do you have to take her out so
you shouldn't make things טמא? tamei? דילמא מיתה, Dilma meisa, we're afraid
she'll die. למימרא דמית אסור במחנה לויה? L'meimra d'meis assur b'machaneh Leviyah?
Remember, where is she standing? She's standing in שער ניקנור, Sha'ar Nikanor,
right right by the line between עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim and עזרת
ישראל. Ezras Yisrael. And the שער ניקנור Sha'ar Nikanor itself is considered
to not have the קדושה kedusha of the עזרה, azarah it's only
עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. So עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim is מחנה לויה,
machaneh Leviyah, not מחנה שכינה. machaneh Shechinah. A dead body is allowed
in מחנה לויה. machaneh Leviyah. Okay, ולמימרא דמית אסור במחנה לויה והתניא
u'l'meimra d'meis assur b'machaneh Leviyah ve'hatanya we learned in
a ברייתא braisa טמא מת מותר ליכנס למחנה לויה, Tamei meis mutar
l'ikanes l'machaneh Leviyah, not only somebody who's in contact with a dead
body, לא טמא מת בלבד אמרו אלא אפילו מת עצמו, lo tamei
meis bilvad amru ela afilu meis atzmo, even the corpse itself, שנאמר
ויקח משה את עצמות יוסף עמו, shene'emar vayikach Moshe es atzmos Yosef
imo, משה Moshe took the bones of יוסף Yosef עמו במחיצתו, imo
bimchitzaso, with him in his camp. משה Moshe was in מחנה לויה.
machaneh Leviyah. So what if she would die? It would be in
מחנה לויה. machaneh Leviyah. I don't know, maybe the body would fall
backwards and into the עזרה? Maybe. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, then it
just- then it
just
should have said like "stand in a way", doesn't have to take
her out.
Let's see the גמרא's Gemara answer. All right, let's see the גמרא's
Gemara answer.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, שמא תפרוס נדה. shema tifros niddah. Ah, no!
We're not afraid she'll die. We're afraid that all this will be
happening to her body and she's going to stain and be a
נדה, niddah, and a נדה niddah is אסור assur in מחנה לויה
machaneh Leviyah because somebody who's טומאה יוצא מגופו tumah yotzei migupo can't
go in מחנה לויה, machaneh Leviyah, which is why they tell people,
I mean, who want to go up to the Temple Mount, they
tell men to go to the מקוה mikvah so that they won't
be a בעל קרי ba'al keri because it's טומאה יוצא מגופו tumah
yotzei migupo is אסור assur on מחנה לויה, machaneh Leviyah, and women
I assume they advise women to make sure that they're not נדות.
niddos. Okay, so that's the problem. And let's get to the end
of this point and then you can ask the questions. So the
גמרא Gemara says, but notice, now that that's the problem, we're not
saying she's going to die. We're not necessarily saying she's going to
die. We're afraid she's going to be a
נדה. niddah. למימרא דביעיתותא מרפיא? L'meimra d'be'isusa marafya? You mean to tell
me that fear causes the- the you know the body to like
loosen, you know like like so it's not holding back the blood,
it's like it's loosening and the blood is flowing. אין, In,
yes, דכתיב ותתחלחל המלכה, dechtiv vatischalchal hamalkah, אסתר Esther trembled מאד, me'od,
אמר רב שפירסה נדה, amar Rav shepirsah niddah, the trembling and she
became a נדה. niddah. So you see that the trembling and the
fear caused her to become a נדה. niddah. והא נן תנן, Ve'ha
nan tnan,
one minute though, we have a משנה that says that if a
woman is hiding in a cave and she's afraid of like that
there are bandits out there or whatever, that she doesn't have to
be afraid even when her- the time of her period comes, she
doesn't have to be afraid that she bled because being in the
state of fear keeps her from becoming a נדה, niddah, keeps her
from bleeding. So which is it? Does fear prevent bleeding or does
it cause it? So the גמרא Gemara says פחדא צמית, pachda tzamit,
fear sort of shrivels up, like tightens, prevents bleeding. ביעיתותא, Be'isusa,
which is like sudden shock I guess would be maybe a translation,
מרפיא marafya that loosens. So the way sort of רש"י explains it
is that פחדא pachda is like anxiety and it's something that you've
been worrying about for a long time. It's not like a sudden,
you know, it's not shock essentially. It's like it's like a fear
that doesn't come suddenly, whereas a fear that seizes you suddenly, that
causes you to loosen and to bleed and really that's the concern
that she'll become a נדה. niddah. So you had a question? No?
Yeah so I- I should have thought of this before but a
woman who becomes a נדה niddah could hold off the סוטה procedure
indefinitely. by just not going to the מקוה. mikveh.
That's a good point, right? The גמרא says they can't bring her
into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. All right, that's a good point.
I don't know if that would be any different from her just
saying איני שוטה, aini shotah, which you know if that's the way
you're going to be, fine, then just get together and be done
with it. Yeah.
So when we take notes on the זכות zechus we really mean
we don't want her to be a נדה niddah and then as
the result the sort of like you know...
Right, I mean that's another interesting point. The concept of תטמא העזרה,
titamei ha'azarah, like the עזרה itself doesn't really become טמא, tamei, right?
A person who is טמא tamei is forbidden and when they enter
it they violate the you know, they transgress, but there definitely is
an idea that the sense of the קדושה kedusha being violated, right?
I mean think about the whole עבודת יום הכפורים avodas Yom Hakippurim
is to cleanse it from טומאת בני ישראל. tumas Bnei Yisrael. Now
that's probably טומאה tumah caused by sin, but nevertheless, like you don't
want things, the reason a טמא tamei person is forbidden to go
is because there's a violation of the קדושה kedusha by having this
טמא tamei thing in the you know, in the holy grounds.
But I was just going to point out that this is, you
know,
consistent with other accounts of like beheadings where like in גיטין, דף
ס״ז, daf samech zayin, where actually a whole bunch of bodily fluids
discharge. Ah, it's like the same idea that the execution will cause
bodily fluids.
Right. I mean I think that's true, like you know, yeah, that's
definitely true that the body like vacates its fluids like particularly in
you know that kind of an assault.
Right, exactly, exactly. Okay, so יש לה זכות, yesh lah zechus, let's
just read now starting about the זכות zechus being תולה. toleh. מאני
מתניתין, mani masnisin, who's our משנה? Because our משנה says one, two,
or three years. לא אבא יוסי בן חנן lo Abba Yossi ben
Chanan ולא רבי אלעזר בן יצחק איש כפר דרום velo Rabi Elazar
ben Yitzchak ish Kfar Darom ולא רבי ישמעאל. velo Rabi Yishmael. There
you are, you're worrying about obscure תנאים. Tannaim. הא פליגי ha peligi
except רבי ישמעאל. Rabi Yishmael. דתניא, detanya, אם יש לה זכות תולה
לשלושה חודשים. im yesh lah zechus toleh lishlosha chodashim.
No, at most three months. כדי הכרת העובר kedei hakaras ha'ubar דברי
רבי אבא divrei Rabi Abba דברי רבי אבא יוסי בן חנן. divrei
Rabi Abba Yossi ben Chanan.
Because he apparently reads the פסוק posuk ונקתה ונזרעה זרע veniktah venizre'ah
zera
that ונקתה veniktah is not only if she's טהורה, tehorah, but if
she's somehow meritorious for another reason she will be cleansed until the
time when ונזרעה זרע, venizre'ah zera, which doesn't mean a child is
conceived but when a conceived child would be visible. Okay, so she'll
be cleansed if she's טהורה tehorah if she somehow meritorious, it will
be held off for this period of time. Okay, at least if
it's three months then you know it's more, it doesn't again, like
make the efficacy suspect in people's eyes. Three months you can you
know check, you'll still remember and check back in. דברי רבי אלעזר
בן יצחק איש כפר דרום אומר תשעה חודשים. divrei Rabi Elazar ben
Yitzchak ish Kfar Darom omer tisha chodashim. No, similar idea, ונקתה
ונזרעה זרע, veniktah venizre'ah zera,
but זרע zera means until the time it takes for a child
to be born. That's how long it'll hold it off. שנאמר ונקתה
ונזרעה זרע shene'emar veniktah venizre'ah zera ולאו אומר velav omer זרע יעבדנו
יסופר, zera ya'avdenu yesupar, the seed that shall serve him will tell.
זרע הראוי לספר, zera hara'uy lesaper, a seed that is you know
that is fit to speak. So I don't know. That'll be years.
I know, it's not when he's just born. Anyways, somehow ונקתה ונזרעה
זרע veniktah venizre'ah zera means it'll be held off until the time
that either a זרע zera could be visible, you know could be
seen that a woman is pregnant or that could be born. That's
how long it'll be held off. רבי ישמעאל אומר שנים עשר חודש,
Rabi Yishmael omer shneim asar chodesh, twelve months. ואף על פי שאין
ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר, ve'af al pi she'ein raya ladavar zecher ladavar,
even though there's not a proof, there's a hint to this, that
merit causes a punishment to be held back for twelve months. דכתיב,
deksiv, it says by דניאל, Daniel, he's the prophet, he gives נבוכדנצר,
Nevuchadnezzar, להן מלכא מלכי ישפר
עלך, lahen malka malki yishpar alach, therefore King, let my advice find
favor in your eyes, because נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar had this dream or whatever
and it resulted in the fact that he wound up like
going like you know in nature whatever, going like wild you know
amongst like naked amongst the animals for like a period of time.
So he calls דניאל Daniel in and he said let my thing
find favor in your eyes. וחטיך בצדקה פרוק, vechatayach bitzedaka ferok,
let your sin be redeemed through righteousness or through charity. ועויתך במיחן
עניין, va'avayach bemichan inayin, and your iniquity through through a kindness or
generosity to the poor. הן תהוי ארכא לשלוותך, hen tehei archa lishalvach,
and that way there will be a you know a length to
your you know your well-being and your tranquility will extend, your peace
will extend. וכתיב uchshiv כלא מטא על נבוכדנצר מלכא, kola meta al
Nevuchadnezzar malka, all these things occurred to, happened to נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar the
king. וכתיב ולקצת ירחין תרי עשר, uchshiv uliktzas yarchin terei asar,
after twelve months, so he basically, he followed דניאל'ס Daniel's advice, he
did all these righteous acts and it forestalled the punishment for a
year. So you see merit forestalls for a year. So okay, so
we have all these different opinions but none of them say three
years. So the גמרא says לעולם רבי ישמעאל le'olam Rabi Yishmael ואשכח
קרא דאמר ותני ve'ashkach kra de'amar vesani דכתיב, deksiv, yes it's רבי
ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael
but there's a פסוק posuk that actually uses, is used as a
multiplier, because it says כה אמר השם על שלושה פשעי אדום ועל
ארבעה לא אשיבנו, ko amar Hashem al shelosha pish'ei Edom ve'al arba'ah
lo ashivenu, right? So three times is understood for three sins you
hold back, so for each sin you could hold back, you know
a year, somehow it means you could hold back three. Three years
for three times. I guess. ומה אף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר
זכר לדבר, umai af al pi she'ein raya ladavar zecher ladavar, what
it means even though there's not a proof, it's a hint.
No, maybe God is slower to punish the non-Jews, you know, maybe
the Jews, God, you know, because God's more exacting with the Jews,
so just because he takes a year for them, you can't say,
or two years or three years, you can't say he'll take the
same for us. Now I want to just say one important thing
about this, which is we shifted from a specific dynamic with a
סוטה ונקתה ונזרעה זרע v'nikta v'nizra'a zara that זכות תולה zechus toleh
to make it this much more generic thing about somebody deserves a
punishment, their merit can hold them back, which has again something nice
to it in terms of like not making this woman like special.
Like we all sin and you know, and we believe God will
punish us for our sins, you know, and merit can hold, forestall
that punishment, so this is just like anybody else who, you know,
whose sins might, I think it, I think it like downplays the
hyperfocus on this, you know, adulterous woman and she's the type of
person that sins and gets punished and nobody else, right? It now
makes it much more, you know, much more generic. But it also
does go back to David's point, which is, you know, it also
switches it as a type of a divine punishment as opposed to
a court proceedings case to help her determine whether she can go
back to her husband, and it really just makes it almost like
between her and God, and therefore your question, well תשובה teshuva should
do the best at forestalling it, right? That's not being discussed. So
you're right, it's bringing us away from that very much almost like
court proceeding type of way to making it like just her and
God and some divinely deserved punishment. So we'll see more about all
of this tomorrow.